A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Harpers Ferry Fund Records, 1859-1861
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Harpers Ferry Fund Records, 1859-1861
The Library of Virginia
APA 145
2.3 cu. ft. (5 boxes)
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
In 1859, John Brown and a band of followers captured the federal arsenal at Harpers Ferry, West Virginia, but were themselves captured by Virginia forces commanded by Robert E. Lee. In 1860 the General Assembly passed several acts authorizing the payment of expenses incurred during the Harpers Ferry raid. The secretary of the commonwealth, the auditor of public accounts, and the adjutant general were appointed commissioners to settle accounts. The board's function was to settle all accounts incurred in assembling, arming, equipping, transporting, and maintaining troops during John Brown's Raid on Harper's Ferry. The auditor of public accounts then issued warrants to the individuals entitled compensation.
Scope and Content
Accounts and receipts, 1859-1861, of the Auditor of Public Accounts Harpers Ferry Fund, arranged chronologically into five boxes. The collection mainly consists of accounts and receipts, but also interfiled are correspondence, payrolls, and warrants. The records document the expenses incurred by individuals and businesses during John Brown's Raid and detail the Auditor of Public Accounts reimbursements to individuals and businesses. For an unknown reason some of the accounts and receipts have warrant numbers, while the earlier accounts and receipts (1859 October - 1860 February) do not have warrant numbers.
Included are accounts and receipts detailing expenses for the transportation, board and lodging, and supplies and equipment of the militia. Notable expenses include clothing, munitions, surgical equipment, food, boarding and feed of horses, advertising, bedding and furniture, building supplies, and damages to local property. Often the name of the regiment was noted on the receipt. Included are some accounts approved by the Virginia Board of Commissioners and signed by George W. Munford, president of the Board. Also included are notes appointing agents to collect fees due individuals.
Of note is a warrant, 14 April 1860, to John Wilkes Booth for military service. As a member of the 1st Virginia Volunteers, Booth received $64.58 for nineteen days' military service. The warrant approving payment is dated 14 April 1860. The oversize materials include payrolls for individual officers and doctors, as well as muster and pay rolls for Capt. James W. Gray's Company of Infantry (67th Virginia Regiment) and Butlers Company of Infantry (Hamtramck Guards).
For additional records please see: Virginia. Board of Commissioners. John Brown's Raid claims and military expenses (LVA Accessions 36955 and 36956) and Virginia. Department of Military Affairs. John Brown's Raid accounts and military records (LVA Accessions 38917, 39025, 39026).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Accounts and receipts, 1859 October. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1859 November - 1860 February [Baltimore & Ohio Rail Road Co.]. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1859 November. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1859 December. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1859 December 3-16. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1859 December 17-21. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1859 December 22-30. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 January. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 January 26-31 [Warrants 2540-2789]. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 January 27 [Warrants 1-58]. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February 1-9 [Warrants 3057-4462]. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February 10-15 [Warrants 4513-4690]. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February 16-18 [Warrants 4704-4794]. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February 18-21 [Warrants 4809-4891]. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February 23-25 [Warrants 4914-4992]. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February 25-29 [Warrants 5001-5091]. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 February 29 - March 7 [Warrants 5112-5297]. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 March. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 March 7-13 [Warrants 5303-5497]. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 March 14-16 [Warrants 5500-5595]. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 March 17-23 [Warrants 5615-5789]. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 March 24-31 [Warrants 5802-5999]. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 March 31 [Warrants 6001-6028]. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 April. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 April 2-4 [Warrants 7020-7236]. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 April 7-21 [Warrants 7316-7493]. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 April 21- May 11 [Warrants 7517-7782]. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 May. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 May 16-22 [Warrants 7852-7982]. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 May 24 - June 8 [Warrants 8013-8280]. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 June 9 - July 14 [Warrants 8300-8913]. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 July 26 - September 19 [Warrants 9063-9828]. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Accounts and receipts, 1860 October [Warrants 238-683]. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Accounts and receipts, 1861. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Accounts and receipts, Miscellaneous 1860. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Accounts and receipts [oversize], 1859-1860. (Box 5, Folder 1-4)